(upbeat music)
- Hello, English learners.
Welcome back to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- And I'm Erica.
- And we're bringing you
another great elementary
lesson for all our
elementary learners.
- You know what, Marco?
I think this lesson is so useful.
This is language that you can
actually use every single day.
- Exactly, every day.
Exactly, because today we're
gonna be teaching you small talk.
- So what is small talk?
- Well, small talk is small conversations
that you would have with people
that you don't know very well,
but you still want to be polite, yes.
- Right, and you want to
maybe just chat a little bit.
- Okay, so let's listen to our dialogue,
and as always, it's gonna be a
little bit fast, but don't worry about it.
- 'Cause welcome back in a minute, and help
you with some of the difficult language.
(upbeat music)
- Morning.
- Hi there, Mr. Anderson.
How are you on this fine morning?
- Fine, thank you.
It sure is cold this morning, isn't it?
I barely even got out of bed.
- Yeah, it's pretty cold, all right.
- Did you catch the news this morning?
I heard that there was
a fire in Byron Street.
- No, I didn't hear about that.
- Did you happen to watch
the football game last night?
The Patriots scored in the last minute.
- No, I don't like football.
- Oh, by the way, I saw you with your
daughter at the office Christmas party.
She's really beautiful.
- She's my wife.
- Ah, she's my floor.
- Nice talking to you, goodbye.
- Oh, sir, this is the 56th floor.
We're on the 70th.
- That's okay, I'll take the stairs.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, I think this guy
was a little bit annoying.
- Yeah, Mr. Anderson really
didn't wanna talk to him, did he?
- Yeah, I think that was pretty obvious.
He left the elevator in a hurry.
Okay, let's take a look at her
language today in language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
- All right, what do we have
today in language takeaway?
- Well, we've got four words and
phrases and our first one is barely even.
- Barely, even.
So how do we use barely even?
It's a little bit difficult.
- It's really similar to like almost
couldn't or almost nothing or almost can't.
So we use it usually in a negative sense.
For example, I could say I was so busy
today, I could barely even eat my lunch.
- Okay, so I can maybe say it was
so dark, I could barely even see.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- Or I'm so poor, I can
barely even pay my rent.
- Okay, good.
Barely, even.
All right, let's take a
look at our next one.
Catch, catch, catch.
Did you catch the news?
- So by, did you catch the news?
You mean, did you hear the news?
- Exactly.
So how else can we use this?
Did you catch?
- A really common one is
I didn't catch your name.
- Yeah, I didn't hear your name.
- I didn't hear your name.
- Yeah, and we can also say
I didn't catch what he said.
- I didn't catch what he said, yeah.
So I didn't hear.
- Yeah.
- Okay, let's look at our
next word, by the way.
- By the way.
- Okay, so let's listen to some examples
first of how we can use, by the way.
And then we'll come
back and talk more about it.
- Example one.
- Are you going to be at the meeting today?
- Yeah, I'll be there.
- Oh, by the way, did you
hear what happened today?
- Example two.
- By the way, I almost
forgot to tell you Maggie Cole.
- Okay, so I see that
when we say by the way,
we're introducing a point after
we've already talked about something.
- Exactly, and maybe it's not even
related to the topic we were talking about.
- No, it's a different topic.
- A different topic, right?
- It's like saying, oh, I
almost forgot to tell you.
- Exactly.
So I was like, oh, Erica, don't
forget we have a meeting today.
Oh, and by the way, I
like your new haircut.
- Thanks, Marco.
- All right, see?
That's the way you would use by the way.
Okay, and our last word
on language, take away.
Take the stairs.
- Take the stairs.
- So it doesn't mean you're
gonna take them somewhere.
- No, no, no, no, you're not
taking them home with you.
It means you're gonna go up the stairs.
- Okay, so take the stairs.
- Yes, a lot of people
might say use the stairs
or go up the stairs, but our English
pod learners they know, right?
- To use take the stairs.
- Yep, take the stairs.
- Okay, so now we're ready
to listen to our dialogue again.
We're gonna slow it down a little bit.
- And this will help you to catch
these phrases a little bit better.
(upbeat music)
- Morning.
- Hi there, Mr. Anderson.
How are you on this fine morning?
- Fine, thank you.
- It sure is cold this morning, isn't it?
I barely even got out of bed.
- Yeah, it's pretty cold, all right?
Did you catch the news this morning?
I heard that there was
a fire in Byron Street.
- No, I didn't hear about that.
- Did you happen to watch
the football game last night?
The Patriots scored in the last minute.
- No, I don't like football.
- Oh, oh by the way, I saw you with your
daughter at the office Christmas party.
She's really beautiful.
- She's my wife.
Oh, here's my floor.
Nice talking to you.
Goodbye.
- Oh sir, this is the 56th floor.
We're on the 70th.
- That's okay, I'll take the stairs.
Okay, so now let's take
a look at ways to start
up some small talk
in putting it together.
Putting it together.
So Marco, today we've
got some great patterns or
structures that you can
use in your small talk.
Yeah, exactly. We saw some great patterns.
Let's start with the first one.
It sure is cold this morning.
It sure is cold.
It sure is cold. Okay,
so we can change it up a
little bit and say it sure
is hot or it sure is late.
Okay, this sure is interesting or
you could say he sure is smart.
So basically you can change the adjective
cold, hot, smart, hard, difficult.
And when you say sure
is, this is a great way of
emphasizing that you
believe this adjective to be true.
Okay, sure is.
Now what would be the answer to this?
Well, in the dialogue, Mr. Anderson
said, yeah, it's pretty cold, all right.
It's pretty cold, all right.
So again, using the
examples we used before,
we can say, oh, it's
pretty hot, all right.
Or it's pretty late, all right.
Or he's pretty smart, all right.
Or this is pretty interesting, all right.
So it means you're
agreeing with that person.
Exactly.
Okay, great.
So Marco, these things, it sure is
blank and yeah, it's blank, all right.
These can go together
really well, can't they?
Yeah, it is a question and
answer format, they go well.
So why don't we listen to some examples
of how these two phrases work together?
Example one.
It sure is a nice day today.
Yeah, it's nice, all right.
Example two.
The boss is sure late today.
Yeah, it's late, all right.
Example three.
This class is really hard.
Yeah, it's hard, all right.
Okay, so now let's take a look at
our next word and putting it together.
Did you happen to?
Did you happen to see Bob this morning?
I didn't happen to see Bob.
So it means like, like, did you buy chance?
By chance, did you buy
chance see Bob or something?
Yeah.
Okay, another example
would be, did you
happen to go to that
restaurant I recommended?
Or maybe, do you happen to have a pen?
Do you happen to know
where the bathroom is?
Yeah, that's a really useful one.
That's a useful one.
That's basically how you
would use this structure.
Did you happen to?
Do you happen to?
So now let's listen to our
dialogue for the third time
and I'm sure that you'll be
able to understand everything.
Morning.
Hi there, Mr. Anderson.
How are you on this fine morning?
Fine, thank you.
It sure is cold this morning, isn't it?
I barely even got out of bed.
Yeah, it's pretty cold, all right.
Did you catch the news this morning?
I heard that there was
a fire in Byron Street.
No, I didn't hear about that.
Did you happen to watch
the football game last night?
The Patriots scored in the last minute?
No, I don't like football.
Oh, by the way, I saw you with your
daughter at the office Christmas party.
She's really beautiful.
She's my wife.
Ah, here's my floor.
Nice talking to you.
Good bye.
Oh sir, this is the 56th floor.
We're on the 70th.
That's okay, I'll take the stairs.
All right, Marco, that was a really
useful dialogue for daily life, wasn't it?
Yeah, I think you
can find a lot of useful
language there and that
you can apply tomorrow.
Yeah, well speaking of useful things,
let's talk a little bit about our website.
Yeah, be sure to go to
our website at englishpot.
com where you can
find other lessons as well.
Maybe you're an intermediate
student or advanced.
Yes, so we've got intermediate, advanced,
upper-intermediate lessons on our website.
And a lot of other resources
that you can explore.
So be sure to come to our
website and leave all your comments
because Erica and I are
always there and we're
really happy to answer
all of your questions.
Okay, everyone, well, we're out of time.
But until next time, goodbye.